you know if i've got a niche let's say
for example i've got the ice age
uh when i've got the ice age woolly
mammoths emerge and are successful
uh but when the ice age ends and we have
a warm period
wooly mammoths go away and it really
doesn't matter what the willie mammoth
want to do
if the niche has changed the niche has
changed those institutional structures
music industry banking pharmaceuticals
medical it doesn't matter effectively
all institutional structures that
evolved in the niche
of scarce information
are almost always going to be quite
significantly unfit for the emergent
niche
of abundant information
i guess i hadn't stopped to think that
the reason why
politics seems so crazy right now
is that the governing that they're
trying to do
across the wealthiest parts of our
country the
the huge institutionalized
things like media and music and money
and pharma and education and
transportation
are in fact becoming super decentralized
and hard to govern all the
money and power and control of those
things are not being held
nearly as tightly as they used to be
we've all watched the disintegration
of power across many of these different
institutions
so it's no wonder as each one of them
begins to fall
that they all fall prey to the same
decentralization of power it for sure
makes you stop and think about where
everything's headed
i know that's not what i had signed up
for when i initially started to talk
to jordan greenhall i thought we were
going to talk about nootropics
and smart drugs and that's where we
started but in short order
jordan aimed the conversation at the
dead center of these trends
i was first made aware of jordan and the
neurohacker collective
at a podcast dinner and recording
for wim hof that chris ryan and i did
and some of his folks from the neuro
hector collective were brought along by
some stanford researchers jordan was one
of the co-founders of divx
he also was at mp3.com and the guys
dabbled in just about anything you could
possibly
imagine from philosophy to role-playing
games
with most of his interests coming back
to the co-evolution of human
civilization and technology
jordan has come to the conclusion that
humanity is in the midst
of a world historical transition and as
he put it
it's likely to kill us all like mad max
or
maybe see us in a amazing future like
star trek
either way humans are going to need a
significant upgrade
to our consciousness and that's what the
neurohacker collective is focused on
you may have heard of their product
qualia a popular nootropic that boosts
your mental capacity
i know for sure it felt like my brain
got an upgrade and yours will feel that
way too at the end of the show
[Music]
this is grow big always i'm sam lawrence
maybe we can start with this i've heard
nootropic i've heard smart drug what's a
smart drug
well actually it's funny there's
probably two ways of describing it one
is what i think is the
the reality is that a smart drug is a
clever way for internet web marketers to
separate people from their money um but
if we want to actually talk about uh the
the you know the more
honest category uh which i think has
been known as no tropics for a while
and then we have to decide what are the
what's the best set of nominal glitch
because it's such an emergent thing
that's not very well understood
um it is the the recognition of the fact
that neurochemistry
is an actual real thing and that we can
use a combination of neuroscience and
molecular biochemistry and pharmacology
to design neurochemical
interventions that change the way that
the
the brain works and therefore change the
way that your cognition
and your psychology work in desired
directions
so you know the old i guess it was the
60s
phrase better living through chemistry
um plausibly actually delivered on
so as i understand it nootropics are a
little bit more like hey how can i
upgrade my
brain is that right
yeah what i would i you know i tend to
come to things from the top
down and uh or the very very bottom up
so
um the idea of no tropics is to say can
we upgrade your conscious experience
in general or more specifically can we
actually upgrade your your adaptive
capacity your ability to be effective in
the world
um and then so below that intent
is the set of more concrete things that
make that possible it's very important
to recognize that
um your adaptation to the world is a
always moving target so
sometimes being more alert is good it's
an
adaptive sometimes being more alert is
maladaptive so it's
it's less about the ability to deliver
on some specific
kind of local concrete upgrade and
actually more about the ability to have
a sense of what is the total portfolio
of capacities that make up a particular
state and then how do we actually try to
one upgrade your portfolio so you have
more ability to respond to the world
and then improve the the total set
so that your your total sort of
responsive capacity
is more adaptive to the total set of
environmental conditions you might find
yourself in
when i think back at this like you said
i guess the idea sprung in the 60s and i
remember being in college and going like
wow i
i really need to i don't know drink more
coffee
or take some stru you know some sort of
drugs or something to kind of get my
focus going here and a lot of it was
cultural right like i had school or i
had
some sort of pressure on me and i wanted
to increase my performance so
i guess just starting at the high level
here is the idea here that
look our culture and our pressures have
increased beyond evolution
and sure mother nature gave us a great
brain but that brain doesn't work in
our culture so we need to do something
in order to enhance performance to meet
the demands that we've got
yeah i think that's a fair way of
putting it um i i would kind of
i would actually put it into more of a
longer term narrative which is that
mother nature gave us a great brain
which has always been
and will always be in relationship to
some kind of pharmacology you know
whether it's just simply
are you consuming fats or carbohydrates
which is going to very significantly
change the way your brain
behaves um or you know are you are you
consuming
coffee or chocolate which are different
chemistries that the brain has been
co-evolving with
since we've had brains um and so there's
there's two movements one movement is
that there's a
continuous coevolutionary process
between the
the body brain system and the the set
of environmental factors that we
interact with
and then the second is that the that
co-evolutionary process
particularly in the middle of the 20th
century began to
quite radically accelerate outside of
the what we call the equilibrium
feedback or the safe space the safe zone
that evolution had prepared us for and
and
we're now kind of an environment where
we bootstrapped ourselves well outside
of what nature prepared us for
and we're now increasingly having to
take
rather deep responsibility for where
we've put ourselves
and so that's interesting so one way of
approaching that
upgrade would be uh i guess using
some sort of chemical biology are there
other
premises around what we'll need to do to
upgrade
our brains beyond the chemical piece
sure absolutely um the scope is
is holistic we have to actually take
into account the whole system so
you know whether you're talking about uh
breathing
breathing is actually a very fundamental
attack the the jamie wheel who's a
friend of ours and a partner of the
project um talks about
all kinds of different ways the
different very specific breathing like
you're breathing
in through your nose and then holding
for a little while and then breathing
out sharply through your mouth
uh changes uh the presence of nitrous
oxide in your bloodstream
so that's a physical act that changes
chemistry in a particular direction but
you also have things that change
you know different forms of breathing
will change um
brainwave states you've got
tonality different making different
sounds like vibrating the the nasal
passages does something so
you can think of it as an unrestricted
tool kit
of different ways that you can engage in
behaviors
that modify physical reality that modify
the mind brain system that then modify
your
cognitive and psychological state right
so it's just kind of a loop of that sort
and ideally what happens is that you
modify your cognitive and psychological
state
so as to have a better perception
of the possible ways to go back into
that loop
and better capacity to make decisions on
how to drive that loop so you actually
get a continuous
up gradient loop if that makes any sense
it does
obviously you've experimented a bunch
with this what is it first of all what
does it even
feel like what do people imagine
what should they imagine with respect to
what it feels like
to be on a nootropic to be
um i guess let's just use the word
hacked a little bit
cognitively so what is that what should
they imagine in their heads what does it
feel like
okay well i'll start from the from this
from the notion of broad
and work my way in so again the the
category
includes all possible ways of modifying
the system uh so as to improve adaptive
performance which means it includes
everything from
increasing emotional resilience to
increasing empathy
to increasing creativity to increasing
divergent thinking to increasing focus
there's actually a whole bunch of
different
subsidiary elements each one of which is
in the broad category
so and they all feel very different
right so if you're if you're
taking a neotropic which radically
increases your empathy
uh you know obviously you're going to
feel more connected to
other people and have a better sense of
their emotional state
whereas by contrast if you take a
nootropic that really quite radically
increases your let's say it increases
your focus
and motivation but actually decreases
your empathy uh then that's going to
feel
different what's interesting is that
you're the idea of parallax you're
familiar with that concept like
one eye and two eyes you actually get
three dimensions if you have two eyes
instead of one
yes if you if you if you explore the the
larger space of neotropics you actually
experiment with okay what does it feel
like to have my empathy increased but my
you know say my divergent thinking
decreased during this tribe my focus
increased my empathy decreased
um you'll actually get this massive
explosion the combinatorial explosion of
parallax of again
have a much better sense of what all the
different
sub components look like feel like
and how they fit together um and then
the hard work begins which is figuring
out how to
[Music]
not over bias in a particular direction
but actually how to weave up
a combination of a base state
that is like a place to return to like
your sort of
foundation that is your general purpose
best place to be and then how to
understand what it is time
to push into a particular more focused
or more narrow state
depending on the context um and that's a
you know
that's an art it's not this is not and
nor will it ever be
a discrete mathematical science is
always going to be an art because we're
always
this is that that great recursion we are
always only responding from who we are
and since we're modifying as who we are
uh there's no way to get out of it like
you're just going to be playing with the
uncertainty
of whether or not the state that you're
in right now is really responsive to the
conditions you find yourself in
so is the notion that you might take a
pill
or do something to yourself
that you can you know discover those
performance areas but then somehow
incorporate it into your normal state so
in other words not
need to go on an ayahuasca trip or
microdose on lsd or whatever because
you've
you've found yourself you've tapped into
some other area and now and are
incorporating it into your steady state
or do you feel like nope this is
something where we really need to be
i don't know just making it part of our
our let's just use the word diet
you know just what we're what we're
disciplined and doing all the time by
enhancing ourselves with these
different techniques or chemicals or
whatever to be our normal state
well it depends on how much energy you
want to put into it and how much you
care
i think that as far as i can tell
and i'm only four to six years old so
there's a
gigantic universe of stuff that i have
no experience with whatsoever
but as far as i can tell um it is
possible to integrate these things into
your normal state
broadly so even the super intense stuff
it is possible through
practices and through deliberate effort
to be able to make that part of your
base
your your normally accessible state um
but you know maybe you don't have 40
years to dedicate to focusing on making
that possible
and it's not that that that important to
your adaptive
capacity to be in life to have it be
part of your base state and so you'll
just reserve it as something that you'll
access through some kind of ally so in
this case perhaps it's a
micro dosing and so you'll say it's okay
i'm never going to spend the time and
energy to become
capable of getting into the micro dosing
state through simple
uh force of will so what i'll do is i'll
just keep that
ready at hand to be able to use when i
need it and i'll only need it say 10
of the time that's a very valid approach
given how huge of a market this seems
like it would be why is there
like not that much research or
scientific
community just embracing this or do i do
i have this wrong
oh no you've got it dead on i think
there's a bunch of different reasons um
so let's see if we can piece pill some
of them apart
um one of them is that there was a
a meaningful backlash to the 60s you
know the the kids in the 60s
uh rushed into something big powerful
important and new
with frankly very little discipline or
discernment um
which created a lot of good stuff
assuming you like rock and roll and
and computers um and also create a lot
of bad stuff and so you then kind of
have the counter counter culture
backlash and a lot of things associated
with the use of chemistry to modify
uh subjective experience they're still
tarred with that brush
and i think we can actually point to
empirical reality for this
the people who are the survivors of the
60s
quite disproportionately for example
opposed things like marijuana
legalization
or silicon microdosing frankly it's just
a legacy of that
that bygone era whereas the the
millennials are
radically less uh concerned about those
uh
prohibitions and they maybe the
millennials are unwise because they
haven't experienced it
but in the event that particular uh kind
of generational bias exists
uh another one which is separate but
related and very important
is the notion that consciousness as a
as a concept um is
is itself actually quite tainted in in
the sciences
and this is changing and it's actually
changing so quite rapidly
but certainly a decade ago uh you know
the old-fashioned
mid 19th century to mid-20th century
tension between religion and science
still
broadly categorized consciousness in the
religion category
and therefore a scientist who played
with consciousness was equivalent to
somebody who's trying to find out how
much the soul weighed
um and it's the kind of thing that just
makes you not get promotion in the
scientific
academy and the scientific academy is is
uh
what's the right term for it pretty
cutthroat so being on the wrong side of
that
aesthetic is not the kind of place that
late 20th century
scientists wanted to be
and then the third is within the the
subdomain
uh let's just call it medicine there is
it has been now for quite some time
actually
since the 60s uh a pretty significant
cultural
gulf between serious
medicine which which allies close to a
serious pharmacology
and naturopathy homeopathy
etc which is not serious and frankly
mostly not true um and so you've got a
an issue that anything that smacks of
coming from the
alternative medicine chinese medicine
naturopath homeopathy world again
carries a
quite tainted brand in the universe of
serious people who
don't either want to take the personal
risk
or don't actually believe that it's
worth taking the personal risk
to test some kind of those kinds of
hypotheses
um and i guess the last is that it's
certainly my experience in my opinion
that most of the scientific academy
has lost a lot of the kind of the
fundamental courage and commitment
to truth to characterize the major arc
of science from the
19th century to the middle maybe into
the late 1970s
and broadly speaking has become a
more of an institution than an
instrument to use uh
carol quigley's term meaning people are
much more concerned with doing the right
thing
than with doing the truth thing
huh does that mean that cultures that
have less of a puritanical
influence on their research
might be further along for example i
know pure acetaminophen has been
studied in europe for a super long time
and used over there so what are the big
cultural differences between us and
europe
well i think the short answer is that
i'm not really the right guy to give you
an answer to that there's a
i don't know um what i do know is that
there's both a cultural and a called a
regulatory
distinction that is quite diverse so
places like
brazil and russia have a hell of a lot
more
actual research done in these categories
and also the individuals in the culture
are less concerned about what the formal
structures tell them to do
this is also true in a lot of the asian
places
but it's a it's really each one is
unique
every discrete region even even europe
which is kind of covered under a single
eu
each european country has its own
different cultural history
and its own different uh regulatory or
institutional
perspective on these kinds of things it
is highly heterogeneous
is part of it also like pharma here is
all about
curing things a lot of what the
framework we're using
in this conversation is about enhancing
things i just wonder like
if if pharma is looking at dementia
right and they're like hey take this
pill
it's supposed to help with dementia with
alzheimer's or this or that
they would not be approaching it with a
framework
that uses and kind of the nootropic
uh look you know use all of these uh
performance-enhancing things they'd be
looking at somehow i don't know
sequestering the problem
or the the the outputs of dementia like
trying to kind of minimize them versus
i don't know change the overall
chemistry of the brain
well we've got a bunch of different
factors that are applying simultaneously
so let's kind of take them each
piece by piece and again i i have not
actually been
inside the pharma industry so what i'm
articulating right now is
more of a derivative of a model of how
industries in general work
and some amount of experience with
actual people inside big pharma so
take this with a grain of salt but the
the basic idea is you've got
the primary driver of pharma is the fact
that you're dealing with something which
is
an evolved industry
inside a a co-evolving regulatory
framework right this is just how
everything works
and so first and foremost pharma
is looking for things where the
size of the market and the return
investment
justifies the rather extraordinary cost
neces
necessary for them to go through the
regulatory
gates to be able to sell anything at all
that's actually quite important uh so
you know if we could provide a solution
to dementia that
was effectively free pharma could not
pursue it um because they have to be
able to actually
extract billions of dollars of revenue
for their products
otherwise they can't justify the cost of
actually going to doing the research
and this is you know decisively
important
the second element is that
because of the regulatory environment
and the way that the regulatory trials
are done
and frankly the current state of our um
epistemology of causation pharma is
broadly limited to
relatively simple uh
causal mechanisms and i don't and when i
say relatively simple i mean the
the specific intervention right so they
tend to focus on
one two or two molecule
uh products that have that they can then
do all the work they do to be able to
prove all the things they need to prove
to be able to get regulatory approval to
bring them to market
but what that means is that if a
particular solution requires say four or
five distinct
interacting causal factors they just
can't even touch it
um and that's that's obviously a
gigantic universe of possibilities that
is not within the scope of what they can
research
um what was the other one that mattered
oh and i guess it's also important to
recognize and this is this is
uh linked back to the first which is
that unfortunately it actually is the
case that in order to be able to
maintain the the business model
curing things is actually not anywhere
near as lucrative as
uh maintaining uh maintaining health
through uh pharmaceutical engagement and
so it's
uh if farmer could make a a product that
could
cure dementia that cost a hundred
thousand dollars or could make a product
that ameliorated the negative
consequences of dementia but you had to
be on it forever
and therefore made 10 million dollars
and they're almost economically required
to go for the latter over the former
they may in fact be in breach of their
fiduciary due to shareholders if they do
the alternative
um so we've got a lot of complexity both
in terms of the scientific approach
that we've received over the past 100
years and what's worked what hasn't
worked
the the physical economic cost of
executing that scientific
approach and then the regulatory and
financial framework of what candy can't
be done
and that's kind of the whole the whole
loop on that side and then you flip to
the other side which is
in the current environment we're just
really just starting to get into it the
the the advent of ubiquitous and
relatively free information
things like you know biohackers being
able to communicate broadly with lots of
biohackers past a critical mass
the quantified self movement and so the
ability to turn
quantifiable data into sensors or
feedback mechanisms that live
at the edge in extremely large numbers
is actually changing the landscape of
what we can do
um in a very important way like it's not
this is it's not a trivial shift it's a
it's a fundamental shift in the nature
of how much
information of what kind and with what
kind of fidelity
we can actually generate and then of
course you have computational resources
resources
and machine learning that
really quite radically opens up new
potentials and being able to explore
in particular much more complex
causal frameworks than the kind of
legacy pharmaceutical methodologies
could explore
so is the toothpaste out of the tube in
the same way
that i mean when you're talking it's
reminding me a little bit of the way
that like the music industry was
disrupted right
through a number of things the internet
um how people publish it who has rights
music labels all that stuff like now is
just a
people are scrambling trying to figure
out how to control it because the
toothpaste went on the tube on it is is
that the way you see
things headed for not just
nootropics but just overall as we're
looking at
even pharma i'll go broader than that i
think i would say that we're headed
there for everything
um and the fact that we're headed there
for everything is important for
everything because there's a feedback
loop
so the way i think about in this
particular way
is i very much use evolutionary models
um because there's you know if i've got
a niche let's say for example i've got
the ice age
when i've got the ice age woolly
mammoths emerge and are successful
uh but when the ice age ends and we have
a warm period
welding amendments go away and it really
doesn't matter what the willie mammoth
what to do if the niche has changed the
niche has changed
and i think that's a very good
conceptual framework for what's going on
broadly
so the the the consequences
of exponential technology particularly
in the domain of information
that began in the late 1970s and
continues to accelerate
are a very very fundamental change
in the niche and those institutional
structures
music industry banking pharmaceuticals
medical it doesn't matter effectively
all institutional structures
that evolved in the niche of scarce
information um are almost
always going to be quite significantly
unfit for the emergent niche
of abundant information
and then it's just a matter of time like
when certain industries like say
newspapers
got hit quickly because their particular
kind of thing was very much
pure information and it wasn't that hard
for the information wave to touch that
transform it to pure information just
suck all the energy out of that system
frankly music would have done exactly
the same thing
but for the fact that the music industry
actually connected deeper into the stack
to law and started using its ability to
influence the law to start
making it so that infra so the natural
movement of music into the information
wave
couldn't happen and it got held back by
pure regulatory
uh pressure in the case of medicine
and pharma you know we're dealing with
things that on the one hand are
vastly more informationally complex
than say music or news um and also with
things that are more deeply connected to
stuff that is not information
you know your physical body and so
they're closer to the or further from
the frontier
of the information way but the
information wave is now hitting them
and as again as tools like quantified
self tools instruments and
different kinds of feedback loops you
know
apps that people use to provide
information different kinds of behaviors
of people
choosing to access and use information
for themselves and taking more
responsibility
over their own bodies than they defer to
other to authorities
stuff like that like as those artifacts
begin to emerge
that enable the transfer of energy or
the transfer of power to happen
then you're going to get somewhere
around an s curve
where you start getting into the bend of
the curve and then you'll see an
accelerating
pull kind of like crossing the event
horizon into a black hole
um an accelerating pull of the energy
out of the legacy
system in this case it's going to be the
kind of the well-being system in general
which broadly for us is
and pharmacology into some new
configuration
which is built upon the more fundamental
architectures of abundant information
curious on your thoughts on who the
players become
um and where the war kind of moves as
the oh i don't know profitable
institutions
like pharma you know i mean just you
named him a whole bunch right if you
music this that right all of these
things become disintermediated
is it governments that are like holy
we need to keep the control and we
need to kind of step in here and try to
uh regulate and put boxes around this
stuff
and it's kind of like the people versus
the state
and uh and and that's the tug of war
that happens once everything's
peanut buttered all over the place or
how do you how do you think yeah i mean
to be honest i think so i think that's
exactly the right way of describing it
um i think we've kind of we've reached
that stage uh so first i think that the
[Music]
on just uh like a level playing field
the the information wave we can also
call it the decentralization wave it
actually is the information wave but
decentralization happens to be
very tightly linked to abundant
information so the the information wave
is already passing through most of the
primary components of
of human life with medicine and food
being kind of the hard nuts at the
center that haven't yet been touched and
physical security military things like
that
but so for example they say bitcoin has
already touched
the money function which is a very very
much at the center of
governance and while we are not yet past
the nape of the curve we're getting
there and it's pretty obvious that we're
getting there to most people who care
about that kind of thing and so
uh as the energy of money and finance
starts getting sucked over into the
information environment
you'll see an accelerating breakdown of
the
the kind of the alliance and the
attractor of the 20th century
institutional forum and that'll show up
as a kind of crisis and frankly i
even think like if you want to have a
good understanding of why it is that our
political systems
seem to be going insane i think this is
actually a big part of it
that there is a an actual crisis going
on in the underlying
infrastructure and assumptions again the
niche
uh in which the late 20th century
uh neoliberal global nation-state
structure
emerged that is pushing that entire
uh into crisis and i said earlier that
it's kind of happening everywhere and
the fact that it's happening everywhere
it's important and this is kind of
a very deep point and it's important to
grasp which is
social systems hang together you know
the
the education system and the labor
system are connected
you you go to elementary school so you
can go to middle school so you can go to
high school
so you can go to college so you can
graduate from college
so you can get a job right if if jobs
didn't give a about college degrees
if there was zero
upside to getting a college degree and
getting a job that was de-linked
then the education system would have
changed long ago
but because they are linked and because
they hang together it actually creates a
feedback loop where changing either one
is actually very difficult
you can't change education unless you
change labor you can't change labor
unless you change education
so that that set of feedback loops
between and among the different
subcomponents of the social system
maintains the integrity of the whole
social system
as being a self-perpetuating attractor
to use
complex systems language and so so then
if you kind of if you think about
it as a as like a field
you can imagine like a sheet of paper
and
kind of on the bottom left corner you
have a a bunch of feedback loops and
there's a hard center look at
like a whirlpool and that's our 20th
century
social structure and in the top right
corner
you have another whirlpool and that's
this emergent information
abundant information social structure
that hasn't yet occurred
and what's happening is that certain
pieces at the edge of the bottom left
corner
are moving across the threshold and
becoming part of the new
attractor part of the new whirlpool and
as they do that
both the old whirlpool begins to lose
its energy because it's got less stuff
that's orbiting it
less feedback moves to maintain its
integrity and the new one
begins to build its energy um
and that's really really important
because things like uh you know how does
an individual human being
behave and participate in the
decentralized economy
it's not like they behaved and
participated in the centralized economy
now you have to have a lot more
capacity loaded on the individual
each individual has has to have more
capacity
to be able to take more responsibility
for what they choose to do
in the world one because their degrees
of freedom are going to be wide open but
two
because the the boxes are not going to
be as coercive
right you're not just going to kind of
get handed off from one machine to
another machine
with a very small amount of choices in
between
you're going to be floating around in a
whole field where every day you can
choose to say okay today i'm going to
actually do learning
i'm going to focus on education it's
what i'm doing today oh well tomorrow
i'm to actually very specifically focus
on self-care and level up my capacity to
engage in a better
way of maintaining my well-being okay
well then for the next two hours i'm
actually going to be engaging in
what otherwise just to be known as work
and i'll add my value to some set of
projects which are useful
and therefore provided more resources to
do the other stuff i want to do so it's
going to be a
really rather vastly different way of
being in the world
and as more and more people are
beginning to grasp that and take on
the leveling themselves up into a higher
higher degree of responsibility
which also means a higher and higher
degree of empowerment then
they have less need for patients with
or connection to the legacy structures
of centralized authority
which breaks those legacy structures
utility
and capacity and begins the process of
forming what do these new structures
look like as a collaboration between
empowered responsible individuals is it
conceivable to think about
then governments or the controlling
aspects of social structures that we
have the governing aspects to be
uh in the future a uh non-geographically
bound entity that
that spans you know that we kind of
participate in and maybe move from thing
to things so it's like
i'm part of a um governing system
that is not necessarily the united
states but it's
some structure that i'm a part of that i
associate with that i kind of get
benefits from
and people can move from structure to
structure or do you see all those things
kind of coagulating into a
one economy one system that we then kind
of move within
well i i kind of want to i think it's
important to make sure that everybody's
um how do we do this right it will
definitely not look like
one world government in a 20th century
sense right that's for sure
uh there's very good reasons to to to
believe that that's the case and the
probably the most important
is that the 20th century model of
governance
um doesn't have enough bandwidth
it doesn't have enough capacity to
receive
and process information and make good
decisions
to deal with the actual complexity of
the world
so it's just structurally impossible
it's kind of like trying to uh
i don't know what's right for the right
metaphor um
it's like trying to fly an airplane with
a calculator it's just not going to get
it done
so what can get it done is actually the
better question
and the answer is much closer to the
mesh work that you described some
actually rather decentralized as
decentralized as
can be done mesh work of governance
units that have apis on how they relate
to each other
and some meaningful portion of it will
in fact still be
geographic because we still have
physical bodies and there are still
major
questions of physicality like food and
water and physical safety
but some major portion of it will also
be highly virtualized
um and there's actually a kind of a cool
term called subsidiarity
which is the principle of governance
should be pushed
into the lowest level where it can
actually be done
and i think that's a pretty good
metaphor um
yet at the same time there will actually
be a lot of things that will actually be
totally global
because it just happens to be the most
effective way to to manage them
and those will tend to be very
lightweight
but and very virtual but also global in
scale
like say the internet there's no real
point in there being
two or three very very separate
internets there's a very high quality
attractor to have a highly decentralized
system which has simple protocols to
enable information to flow seamlessly
across it
being a single unified protocol jordan
you have to be on heavy nootropics right
now because you're clearly way smarter
than i am
let me ask you a question how did you go
from like i used to be in
tech i guess i kind of still am uh and
then i moved out a little bit and
have been doing different stuff and i
know you probably
think of yourself somewhat similarly how
do you go from like
you know your past life part of the tech
community and now all of a sudden into
nootropics and
this whole other different world how did
you get pulled into it
um well actually in fact i think it's
it's more that i always was part of it
so
um here's a good here's a good example
in 2005 i was having conversations with
the good folks at google about uh
potentially buying my company
devex and uh unbeknownst to myself
and i was i live in san diego right so
i've i'm i am not
and have never been actually part of
silicon valley quas silicon valley i've
never lived there i've never spent
more than a couple of weeks there um
obviously my business is tech and so i
have a great deal of familiarity with it
but i'm not actually in it after the
neck
so i show up and i'm sitting in the
waiting room to have a conversation with
sergey i think
and i also i have have my hands a book
of
french philosophy um by a philosopher
named g de louis
and i'm just sitting there reading this
book and uh chris sacca
who was at google still at the time and
happened to be the guy who was helping
navigate this thing
came in and started talking to me about
what's gonna happen he looked at him he
was just he noted
that he was a little bit surprised that
i was reading
such a thing and i think that's
that's a good um a good narrative
that is much closer to the center who i
have always been
i did philosophy undergrad i also did
compsci
ai economics political science political
theory
agriculture but always at the top of the
stack because i was just most interested
in those things which the most
durable and either most fundamental or
most emergent um and then
from a personality perspective i just
grew up as a nerd
i just happened to be the guy who liked
computers video games of all sorts role
playing games board games comic books
science fiction all that kind of stuff
and so my my identity the who i am
was just very deeply connected with nerd
culture my
uh predilection was focusing on things
that are either fundamental or emergent
and those two things in 1994
happened to overlap in doing things in
tech
and so that's how i got into tech by
virtue of that but
in many ways it was always a means to an
end my objective has always been
focusing on where is this thing going
and how do we
do the best job as a whole in this giant
story of
humanity in the universe and then
subsidiarily how what role does
technology play
broadly and then below that level what
role can i play in the evolution of
technology in alignment with
that bigger picture help everybody
get super geeky too what kind of stuff
are you reading should they be reading
how do they learn more
about neuro hacker like just aim folks
to places
great uh so it turns out there's
actually a very nice uh
easy answer to that right now with
regard to neuro hacker which which is
jamie's book
stealing fire um he covers
a lot of the primary territory and he
probably covers it in a fashion which is
both
uh true and digestible
so it's the kind of thing that it'll be
one of those things if you haven't read
it in the next year
people will be wondering what value
you've been up to
um and you can think of that as caller
level up tech
the whole set of tech that's existed
since the greek
elissenian mysteries then although it's
a contemporary environment on how do we
actually collectively go about
solving the problem of having enough
individual capacity to deal with the
we're dealing with
okay so aside from that nerding out i
mean
beyond that when i nerd out i mean i
nerd out big time um there's
a pretty good comic book called
unflattening
i actually think comic books are an
excellent vehicle
for understanding stuff because they
have the ability to use
visual and text simultaneously which
actually are two very different
modalities of expression
and then flattening specifically plays
with that it gives you a better sense of
why it is i say what i just said
if you want to go even deeper i would
take a look at the contemporary or the
best current works on
uh the lineage from marshall mcluhan
do you remember him the medium is the
message oh yeah
you know his stuff was hot and then got
cold and but then
a whole bunch of people have held on to
it and it's actually frankly fundamental
like the linkage between
psychology or neuropsychology how our
how our brain
forms our psychological experience
the relationship between that and the
developmental environment of the
technology
uh that mediates our relationship to the
world you know the kind of tech that we
used particularly during our
first 20 years of life and what that
implies
for how we make sense of the world and
how we act in the world is
actually fundamental like if you get
that you can make some really good
predictions
about what's going on next um
i think the next right now this is
actually quite interesting i believe
we're actually in a moment a pretty
significant acceleration
it's very difficult for people to write
books
that are able to keep up with the pace
of change i mean there's a bunch of good
ones i i really quite like
the secrets of our success which is a
a collection of some of the best
thinking right now
on uh developmental anthropology and
what it is precisely that makes human
homo sapien sapiens a cultural
animal um and by the way the deep
insight there is that the fact that
homo sapiens discovered a different two
different
male hierarchical structures one is a
dominance hierarchy
there's a prestige hierarchy and that
turns out to be very very important
um but what i'm actually seeing right
now is it's more of a list of the people
who are
have made have already done enough work
to be able to do a really high quality
of curation
and then are filtering both real-time
and
celebrities like alex lightman for
example
is continuing to do a very good job of
orienting things towards
what's true um and away from and to
what's important um honestly what i
would do is exact opposite
rather than sort of think of the things
that should be i'd actually think of the
things that shouldn't be
um my primary recommendation to
everybody
is turn almost everything off
most forms of
information curation most of the
techniques particularly everything that
is commercial
at any scale and definitely anything
that's commercial any scale that existed
before to call it
2010 is bad for you
um it's not going to be working in your
best interest and it's probably
optimized to make it hard for you to
make sense yourself like it's actually
jacking your olympic system
so broadly speaking turn off your tv
almost entirely
don't read newspapers and be extremely
careful like don't participate
in facebook or most of the twitterverse
like
it's almost like you know the the
learnings that we had in nutrition
stop eating sugar uh be more thoughtful
about the kinds of fats you take in
that level of nutritional discernment
has to be applied to your informational
diet
at least at that level and probably even
higher um
because it moves so much faster amen
brother walk away from all the
institutions
yeah jordan i want to thank you for
being a grow big always this is awesome
stuff
i invite everybody to uh check out
neurohacker collective
and and all those resources there's a
lot of reading it sounds like i need to
catch up on so thanks a whole bunch for
being on grow big always
you're quite welcome i enjoyed it thank
you
a huge thank you to jordan for doing the
show
and thanks to you guys for heading over
to the itunes store to write a review
of the grow big always podcast really
helps with our discoverability
if you haven't done that be sure to head
over there and do it and
while you're online check out the
growbigalways.com
website where all of the previous
episodes are listed
as well as the opportunity to sign up
for our weekly newsletter
i'm incredibly grateful for everyone who
shared the show thanks for listening